Louis-Alexandre Berthier Collection, 1780-1783: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Special Collections.
- Series 4: Return of the French Army from Virgina to Boston, July - December, 1782, dates not examined; more than 48 packets
  - 108. Plans des différents camps occupés par l'Armée aux ordres de M. Le comte de Rochambeau, undated; more than 46 packets 46 pp 32 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39)
    - 118. Camp à Charles Thoon-Ton's house, Le 11 Juillet, 8 miles de Bowling-green, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-10)
      MS, No. 39-10. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, pp. 176-177]
    - 119. Camp à Falmouth, Le 12 Juillet, 1/2 mile de Carles Thoon Ton's house. Le 13 Sejour, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-11)
      Eleventh Camp at Falmouth. 12-16 July 1782. Fourteen miles from the precious camp. There was a "sejour," or extra day's rest here for each of the four divisions, so that two were in camp at the same time, as shown. The officers took advantage of the halt to make excursions in the vicinity. Clermont-Crèvecœur (p. 73)mentions a call on General Washington's mother in Fredericksburg (on the south bank of the Rappahannock, opposite Falmouth). Von Closen (pp. 210-211) speaks of visits to William Fitzhugh's house (Chatham) and to General Alexander Spotswood's estate at New Post. Blanchard ([1], p. 110) states that he set up and left at Falmouth a temporary hospital for 60 sick, who were later brought to Baltimore.
      MS, No. 39-11. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 177]
    - 121. Camp à Garrot's Tavern, Le 14 Juillet, 13 miles de Falmouth. (Les Eaux n'étant pas assez abondantes, les Divisions Suivantes Campèrent Trois miles plus loin à Peyton's tavern.), undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-12)
      Twelfth Camp at Peyton's Tavern. 15-17 July 1782. As explained in the heading, the First Division had camped on 14 July at "Garrot's" Tavern, 13 miles frrom the previous camp at Falmouth, but because of insufficient water there the divisions following continued 3 miles farther to camp here at Peyton's Tavern. Several of the officer's journals metnion the hot weather and consequent importance of good spring water: e.g., Verger, p. 159. Peytons's Ordinary, as the tavern was also called, was a few miles north of Stafford (county seat of Stafford County, on present U.S. Route 1). The stream shown here is Aquia Run according to Colles, Survey, Plate 68.
      MS, No. 39-12. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 177]
    - 122. Camp à Dumphris, Le 15 Juillet, 10 miles de Peyton's Tavern, et 13 de Garrot's Tavern, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-13)
      Thirteenth Camp at Dumfries. 15-18 July 1782. Ten miles from the previous camp at Peyton's Tavern. Dumfries, county seat of Prince William County, on Quantico Creek (the stream shown here), was once a flourishing port; it was later eclipsed in this respect by Alexandria.
      MS, No. 39-13. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 177]
    - 123. Camp à Colchester, Le 16 Juillet, 10 miles de Dumphris, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-14)
      Fourteenth Camp at Colchester. 16-19 July 1782. Ten miles from the previous camp at Dumfries. The town of Colchester, near the mouth of Occoquan Creek (east of present U.S. Route 1), was already in a state of decline when the French army camped nearby. Verger (p. 159) describes it as "almost deserted." The infantry was ferried across the Occoquan, but the artiller was obliged to use a ford 4 miles upstream. The road to the for ( chemin du gué) is indicated on the map. Chastellux describes a meeting here with General Daniel Morgan: "I was then at Colchester, where the first division of the troops had just arrived, after having crossed in boats a small river that flows near this town. The baggage train and the artillery had taken another route to reach a rather difficult ford. General Morgan met the baggage train when it was engaged in a narrow gorge, and finding that the wagoners were not managing very well, he stopped and showed them how they should drive their wagons. After having put everything in order, he called at my quarters and had dinner with me. The simplicity of his bearing and the nobility of his manners reminded me of those ancient Gallic or Germanic chiefs, who, when at peace with the Romans, came to visit them and offer assistance. He expressed great attachment to the French nation, and great admiration for the fine appearance of our troops... ." Chastellux (4), II, 581.
      MS, No. 39-14. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 178]
    - 124. Camp à Alexandrie, Le 17 Juillet, 15 miles de Colchester, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-15)
      Fifteenth Camp at Alexandria. 17-20 July 1782. Fifteen miles from the previous camp at Colchester. The road from Colchester, corresponding roughly to present U.S. Route 1, crossed Hunting Creek (not included on this map) before coming into the town. The two small creeks shown here have subsequently been filled in. The "Meeting house" is the Old Presbyterian Meeting House, built in 1774 and still standing on South Fairfax Street between Wolfe and Duke Streets. The army's camp seems to have been in the general vicinity of the present junction of Route 1 and the Mount Vernon Memorial Highway. George Grieve, who saw the French army in Alexandria, mentions that their camp was on the ground previously occupied in 1755 by General Braddock's army; see his description cited above, Verger's journal, n. 121.
      On the way from Colchester to Alexandria several of the French officers had turned aside from the route to visit Mount Vernon, where Mrs. Washington was in residence. See, e.g., Von Closen, pp. 212-214, and Blanchard (1), p. 111. It was at this time that Colonel Custine (commanding the Saintonge Regiment) presented to Mrs. Washington a set of porcelain from his factory at Niderviller in Lorraine.
      MS, No. 39-15. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. As an example of the slight variations between the two sets of maps, it may be noted that in this instance the words "Meeting house" have not been filled in on the Rochambeau copy. [Rice/Brown, p. 178]
    - 125. Camp à 1 miles 1/2 au delà de George's Town. Le 18 Juillet, 8 miles d'Alexandrie, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-16)
      Sixteenth Camp, a Mile and a Half beyond Georgetown. 18-21 July 1782. Eight miles from the previous camp at Alexandria. Details concerning the ferries over the Potomac, which the had crossed before reaching Georgetown (then in Maryland) on the east bank of the river, are given in the description of the wagon train's 1781 march in the opposite direction, in Itinerary 6. The stream shown here is a small segment of Rock Creek in what is now the city of Washington, D.C. The camp was located on high ground on the east bank of the creek, presumably in the vicinity of the present P Street Bridge, along the road from Georgetown to Bladensburg. In 1782 the District of Columbia was still in the future and L'Enfant's geometric grid had not yet been superimposed on the old road pattern. Cf. Colles, Survey, Plate 65.
      The army had covered the route from Williamsburg to Georgetown--167 miles according to the mileage figures on the maps--in 18 days (2 of them halts) and 16 marches. The wagon train, when proceeding southward by forced marches over roughly the same route in September-October 1781, had covered it in 12 daily marches (no halts). Although the mileage estimates for the two marches do not exactly coincide, it would appear that the average daily march for the army in July 1782 was a bit over 10 miles, whereas that for the wagon train in 1781 had been over 16 miles a day.
      MS, No. 39-16. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 179]
    - 126. Camp à Blandensburg, Le 19 Juillet, 8 miles de George's Town. Le 20 et 21 Séjour, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-17)
      Seventeenth Camp at Bladensburg [in Maryland]. 19-24 July 1782. Eight miles from the previous camp near Georgetown. Each division had an extra two-days' halt here. The stream is in the Anacostia River. The road at lower right, coming in from Annapolis, is the route by which the wagon train led by L.-A. Berthier had arrived on 23 September 1781. Although it only passed through Bladensburg without stopping to camp, the itinerary describing its route (Itinerary 6) notes that, if the army camped here, "headquarters would be well lodged on either side of the river,.. .there are fine campsites here, as well as pastures and forage."
      MS, No. 39-17. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 179]
    - 127. Camp à Snowden-iron-Work's, Le 22 Juillet, 13 miles 1/2 de Blandensburg, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-18)
      Eighteenth Camp at Snowden's Iron Works [Laurel, Maryland]. 22-25 July 1782. Thirteen and a half miles from the previous camp at Bladensburg. Snowden's Iron Works was on the patuxent River. Major Thomas Snowden's house, shown here, is "Montpelier," still standing on present State Route 197. Verger's journal (p. 160) designates the camp as "Rose's Tavern," also shown on the map.
      MS, No. 39-18. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 179]
    - 128. Camp à Spuriers Tavern, Le 23 Juillet, 9 miles de Snowden-iron-Works, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-19)
      Nineteenth Camp at Spurrier's Tavern. 23-26 July 1782. Nine miles from the previous camp at Snowden's Iron Works and 13 miles from the next camp at Baltimore. Spurrier's Tavern was near present Waterloo on U.S. Route 1. According to Von Closen (p. 215), the camp was "near Spurrier's Tavern...not far from Dorsay's house." At this point the army rejoined the route of its southbound march in September 1781. At that time it had reached Spurrier's Tavern when news of the arrival of La Villebrune's ships, with adequate transports, determined the march southeastward to Annapolis. Cf. No. 162 and notes to Nos. 80 and 82.
      MS, No. 39-19. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, pp. 179-180]
    - 129. Camp à Baltimore, Le 24 Juillet, 13 miles 1/2 de Spurier's Tavern. Séjour Jusqu'au 24 Aoust, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-20)
      Twentieth Camp at Baltimore. 24 July - 24 August 1782. During its month-long encampment here the army's positions were more extended than during the brief stop in Baltimore in September 1781; cf. Nos. 80 and 81. This time the camp stretched southward from a point near present Franklin and Paca Streets (left of map) to a point near Hanover and Lee Streets. The steam west of the camp (shown at bottom of map) flowing into Ridgeley's Cove was the Chatsworth Run, now lost beneath city pavements. Lauzun's Legion is shown in an advanced position on another height, in the vicinity of the present "old" Roman Catholic Cathedral (designed by Latrobe, dedicated in 1821).
      When the army reached Baltimore, its subsequent destination was not generally known, though it was a matter of much specualtion among all the ranks. The decision to march north to join the Americans on the Hudson had been made at a conference between Rochambeau and Washington in Philadelphia, 19 July (cf. Clermont-Crèvecœur's journal, n. 155), and was subsequently confirmed in Washington's letter to Rochambeau, 16 August 1782 (Writings of GW, XXV, 26-28). "I am of opinion," Washington wrote from his headquarters at Newburgh, "that no good consequences can result from your remaining at Baltimore, but that many advantages may attend your marching forward and forming a junction with this Army."
      When the army marched north—the First Division on 24 August—Rochambeau left behind the detachments under La Valette and Chazelles that had been transported there from Virginia, as well as a hospital. They remained until May 1783, when they returned directly to France. Thus several hundred French soldiers were in Baltimore for nine month or so longer.
      MS, No. 39-20. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 180]
      Accounts of the sojourn in Baltimore are included in the journals of Clermont-Crèvecœur (pp. 73-76) and of Verger (pp. 160-161). Clermont-Crèvecœur notes that the camp was "on a charming site in the midst of woodland near the city, from which we enjoyed a most agreeable view."
    - 131. Camp à la forge de Whitemarsh, Le 24 Aoust, 12 miles de Baltimore, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-21)
      Twenty-first Camp at White Marsh Forge. 24-27 August 1782. Twelve and a half miles from the preceding camp in Baltimore. The army marched in fourdivisions, with Lauzun's Legion vanguard, as far as Trenton. The camp at White Marsh Forge was some 3 miles northeast of the so-called White Marsh camp where the army had stopped on its way south in September 1781; see No. 79. The "Etang" shown on the map is a pond formed by a dam in Honeygo Run, which flows into White Marsh Run, where the forges is also shown. White Marsh Run is the head of Bird (or Back) River, which in turn flows into the Great Falls of the Gunpowder River.
      MS, No. 39-21. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 181]
    - 132. Camp à Bush Town, Le 25 Aoust, 12 miles 1/2 de la forge de White marsh, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-22)
      "Twenty-second Camp at Bush Town." 25-28 August 1782. Twelve and a half miles from the preceding camp at White March Forge. The army had bivouacked here at Bush, in a slightly different position, in September 1781; cf. No. 78. The main road leading through the town is present State Route 7. The road branching off to the left is the "road to Bald Friar Ford" (present Maryland State Road 136). On this northward march the entire army proceeded direclty to Lower Ferry, whereas the previous year the artillery and wagons had made a detour via Bald Friar Ford (see note to No. 77). The building shown at the right of the map is Bush Mill; the millrace can be traced from Bynum Run across the highway to the mill.
      MS, No. 39-22. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, pp. 181-182]
    - 133. Camp à Lower ferry, Le 26 Aoust, 12 miles de Bush Town. Le 27 Séjour, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-23)
      Twenty-third Camp at Lower Ferry. 26-30 August 1782. Twelve miles from the preceding camp at Bush. There was an extra day's halt here for each of the hour divisions. In September 1781 the army had bivouacked on the west bank of the river (present Havre de Grace side), as shown on map, No. 77. This time the camp was on the east bank (present Perryville side). The entire army, including the artillery and wagons, was ferried across. Von Closen (then accompanying General Rochambeau, who was riding with the First Division) notes in his journal (pp. 227-228) that boats and "skows" had been sent on ahead from Baltimore. "Before crossing the river," he adds, "we had an excellent lunch at the house of the proprietor of the ferry, where we saw one of the pretty local girls--referred to thereaftter in our conversation as Miss Susquehanna."
      MS, No. 39-23. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 182]
    - 134. Camp à Head-of-Elk, Le 28 Aoust, 15 miles de Lower ferry, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-24)
      Twenty-fourth Camp at Head of Elk [in Maryland]. 28-31 August 1782. Fifteen miles from the preceding camp at Lower Ferry. The stream shown at right is Big Elk Creek. The entire army had been united here at Head of Elk the previous year when expecting to embark for transportation down the Chesapeake Bay. Cf. No. 76. The present map does not show the waterfront at Elk Landing, since it had no significance during the 1782 march. The slightly different locations of the two encampments can be determined by reference to the triangular road intersection shown on both maps.
      MS, No. 39-24. Another copy of the map forms part of Rochambeau's set of the northbound camps, Library of Congress, Map Division. The words "Head-of-Elk Bridge" do not appear on the Rochambeau copy. [Rice/Brown, p. 182]
    - 135. Camp à Newport, Le 29 Aoust, 16 miles 1/2 d'Head-of-Elk, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-25)
      Twenty-fifth Camp at Newport [in Delaware]. 29 August - 1 September 1782. Sixteen and a half miles from the preceding camp at Elkton, Maryland. The route from Elkton to Newport--the same taken in the opposite direction the previous year—is shown on the road map, No. 60. The Second Brigade had camped here in Newport in 1781 (cf. No. 59), but in a position differing slightly from the one shown on the present map of the 1782 encampment (by divisions). The main road, to the right of which the army camped, is present Market Street (State Route 4). THe street intersecting this, at the top of the map, is State Route 41.
      The next camp was at Chester, Pennsylvania. The army thus marched through Wilmington without camping there, as one brigade had done in 1781 (cf. No. 75). It may also be noted here that the Lauzun Legion, which remained in America after the rest of Rochambeau's army had departed, was quartered in or near Wilmington during the winter of 1782-1783. It embarked for France, with the detachments left at Baltimore, in May 1783. The exact location of the Legion's cantonment in Wilmington has not been determined; no map of it was been found by the Editors.
      MS, No. 39-25. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, pp. 182-183]
    - 136. Camp à Chester, Le 30 Aoust, 15 miles de Newport, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-26)
      Twenty-Sixth Camp at Chester [in Pennsylvania]. 30 August - 2 September 1782. Fifteen miles from the preceding camp at Newport, Delaware. The camp was to the northeast of the town of Chester, along the road to Philadelphia, on high ground between the two streams shown here: Ridley Creek at the bottom of the map, and Crum Creek at the top. This is in the general vicinity of the present Baldwin Locomotive Works. The 1781 camp had been southwest of Chester; cf. Nos. 58 and 74.
      MS, No. 39-26. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 183]
    - 137. Camp à Philadelphie, Le 31 Aoust, 16 miles de Chester. Le ler Septembre Séjour, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-27)
      Twenty-seventh Camp at Philadelphia. 31 August - 4 September 1782. Sixteen miles from the preceding camp near Chester. The four divisions, preceded by Lauzun's Legion as a vanguard, marched on successive days through the city to their camp on its northern outskirts; the previous year the camp had been on the banks of the Schuylkill near the present Market Street Bridge (cf. No. 73). There was at least one extra day's halt here for each of the divisions. The map shows three regiments and three artillery units, as well as Lauzun's cavalry (yellow and white), in camp at the same time. The First Division (including the Bourbonnais Regiment) resumed its march northward on 2 September.
      The camp ground was along the eastern side of the "Chemin de German Town," indicated on the map as a continuation of Second Street. It was on high ground north of Cohocksink Creek, the larger o the two streams shown, with a dike ("Digue") across its mouth. The smaller stream, marking the northern limit of the regular street grid, is Pegg's Run, also known as Conocuonocue Creek. Both streams have long since been obliterated. The French camp was thus in the general vicinity of the junction of present North Second Street and Germantown Avenue. An interesting comparison can be made between this 1782 camp plan and John Hill's "Plan of the City of Philadelphia" (engraved and published, 1797). The Hills plan, on which the locality is called "Bath," shows that streets had been laid out and many houses constructed there during the postwar years.
      The army resumed its march northward by the road designated here as "Chemin de Read-Lyon's Tavern" (Frankforn Avenue). The stay in Philadelphia, with its attendant festivities, is described in the journals of Clermont-Crèvecœur (pp. 77-78) and Verger (pp. 162-163).
      MS, No. 39-27. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 183]
    - 138. Camp à Sommerset Court House, Le 8 Septembre, 14 miles de Prince-Town, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-28/31)
      Thirty-first Camp at Somerset Courthouse [Millstone, New Jersey]. Also "Camp à Read Lion T., Le 2 Septembre, 15 miles de Philadelphie - manque" [no map], "Camp à Trenton, Le 3 Septembre, 16 miles de Read Lion Voyés campagne 1781, 25eme Camp. Le 4, 5, et 6 Sejour" [no map], "Camp à Prince-Town, Le 7 Septembre, 12 miles de Trentown. Voyés campagne 1781, 24e Camp" [no map]. 8-9 September 1782. Fourteen miles from the preceding camp at Princeton. The camp ground at Somerset Courthouse was in a slightly different location from that of 1781, as can be seen by comparison with maps Nos. 53 and 68. This time two regiments were placed on the bank of the Millstone, east of the road and opposite the church. The main road shown here is present State Route 533; the second (from the top) of the three roads crossing the Millstone and leading to New Brunswick is approximately present State Route 514.
      As indicated in the heading, no new maps for the preceding camps at Red Lion Tavern (28th), Trenton (29th), and Princeton (30th) are included in this series, the army having camped in the same positions as in 1781; cf. Nos. 72, 70, and 69. On the present march, after leaving Trenton, the army marched northward through New Jersey by brigades: the First included the Bourbonnais and Royal Deux-Ponts regiments, the Second, the Saintonge and Soissonnais. Covering the main corps on its right, the Lauzun Legion, commanded by Colonel Robert-Guillaume Dillon, took a route farther to the east, proceeding in seven marches via (1) Kingston, (2) New Brunswick, (3) Scotch Plains, (4) Chatham, (5) The Forks (Two Bridges), (6) Paramus, and (7) Kakiat (New Hempstead, New York) before joining up with the army at Haverstraw prior to crossing the Hudson at King's Ferry. At this time the enemy still occupied New York, and there were rumors of reinforcements arriving there. See Von Closen's journal, p. 234, and Verger's journal, n. 145.
      MS, No. 39-28/31. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, pp. 183-184]
    - 139. Camp à Bullion's Tavern, le 9 Septembre, 13 miles de Sommerset-Court-house, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-32)
      Thirty-second Camp at Bullion's Tavern [Liberty Corner]. 9-10 September 1782. Thirteen miles from the preceding camp at Somerset Courthouse (Millstone). The same route had been taken in the opposite direction in 1781. See No. 53 and also No. 67 for the 1781 camp at Bullion's Tavern. The locations of the two encampments differ slightly. The pattern of roads shown on the map can readily be recognized in the present village of Liberty Corner. The "chemin de Somerset-Court-house," lower right, is present State Route 525, coming into Liberty Corner over Second Watchung Mountain from Martinsville. The road to Whippany (the next day's destination), upper left, is the road from Liberty Corner to Lyons and Basking Ridge.